<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>fisheries acoustics | Echospace @ UW</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/tag/fisheries-acoustics/</link><atom:link href="https://uw-echospace.github.io/tag/fisheries-acoustics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>fisheries acoustics</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 15:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://uw-echospace.github.io/images/icon_hu9a3e81eca2a83564e549c2cdc32b0637_27049_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>fisheries acoustics</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/tag/fisheries-acoustics/</link></image><item><title>Machine learning in fisheries acoustics</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/2021-hake-workflow/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 17:02:36 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/2021-hake-workflow/</guid><description>&lt;p>Active acoustic data collected with scientific echosounders from acoustic surveys have become essential for stock assessment in fisheries resources management. Over the past three decades, a wide suite of physics-based acoustic scattering models were developed to allow translating acoustic observations to biological quantities, such as biomass and abundance, for different marine organisms. In parallel, quantitative scientific echosounders have progressed from specialized equipment to one of the standard instruments on fisheries survey vessels.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To take full advantage of these large and complex new datasets, in this project we aim to combine the development of machine learning methodology with a cloud-based workflow to accelerate the extraction of biological information from fisheries acoustic data. This project is in close collaboration with the
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/west-coast/sustainable-fisheries/fisheries-engineering-and-acoustic-technologies-team" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fisheries Engineering and Acoustics Technology (FEAT) team&lt;/a> at the NOAA Fisheries
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/about/northwest-fisheries-science-center" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Northwest Fisheries science center (NWFSC)&lt;/a> and uses data collected in the past 20 years off the west coast of the U.S. from the
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/west-coast/science-data/joint-us-canada-integrated-ecosystem-and-pacific-hake-acoustic-trawl-survey" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Joint U.S.-Canada Integrated Ecosystem and Pacific Hake Acoustic-Trawl Survey&lt;/a> (aka the &amp;ldquo;Hake survey&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding agency&lt;/strong>: NOAA Fisheries&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Scalable, cloud-native processing of water column sonar data</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/2021-cloud-workflows/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 16:56:36 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/2021-cloud-workflows/</guid><description>&lt;p>Scientists commonly use active sonar systems to collect data about mid-trophic level animals like zooplankton and small fish, which play an important role in the marine ecosystems. Echosounders, or fish-finders, are high-frequency sonar systems that emit pulses of sound and record the reflections from animals, the seabed, and other objects. These instruments have been proven to be more efficient and effective for collecting data over a large survey area or a long time period than many other sampling methods, such as underwater imaging and net trawls. This technology has been widely adopted by the ocean science and commercial fishing communities and more recently has been integrated with autonomous vehicles, resulting in a massive amount of data. However, these datasets can be difficult to analyze and are often underutilized. We will address this issue by adopting and advancing data standards, developing a streamlined data processing workflow, and integrating open-source software tools that capitalize on recent advancements in cloud computing technologies to efficiently transform large quantities of ocean sonar data into information that is useful for exploring, monitoring, and managing living marine resources.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding agency&lt;/strong>: NOAA Office of Ocean Exploration and Research
&lt;a href="https://oceanexplorer.noaa.gov/news/oer-updates/2021/fy21-ffo-schedule.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FY2021 grants&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Pattern discovery from long-term echosounder time series</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/2019-ooi-mtx-decomp/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 14:50:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/2019-ooi-mtx-decomp/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding agency&lt;/strong>: National Science Foundation
&lt;a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1849930&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Award #1849930&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Scalable, interoperable processing of water column sonar data for biological applications using the echopype Python package</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202110-ioos-dmac/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 15:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202110-ioos-dmac/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Building a toolbox for studying marine ecology using large ocean sonar datasets</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202110-uw-data-sci/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 16:30:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202110-uw-data-sci/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>