<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>fisheries acoustics | Echospace @ UW</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/tag/fisheries-acoustics/</link><atom:link href="https://uw-echospace.github.io/tag/fisheries-acoustics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>fisheries acoustics</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://uw-echospace.github.io/images/icon_hu9a3e81eca2a83564e549c2cdc32b0637_27049_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>fisheries acoustics</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/tag/fisheries-acoustics/</link></image><item><title>Machine learning in fisheries acoustics</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/hake-ml/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 17:02:36 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/hake-ml/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://storymaps.arcgis.com/stories/e245977def474bdba60952f30576908f" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Active acoustic data collected by echosounders&lt;/a> (high-frequency sonar systems) play a crucial role in marine ecological research and fisheries stock assessments. Recent technical advancements has further integrated echosounders onto many ocean observing platforms, leading to the rapid accumulation of echosounder data worldwide.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this project, we tackle the challenge of translating experiences from human experts into machine learning models capable of efficiently extracting biological information from large echosounder dataset. Using the rich dataset collected by the
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/west-coast/science-data/joint-us-canada-integrated-ecosystem-and-pacific-hake-acoustic-trawl-survey" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Joint U.S.-Canada Integrated Ecosystem and Pacific Hake Acoustic Trawl Survey&lt;/a> dated back to early 2000s, we are developing deep learning models to automatically annotate echograms—color-coded visual representations of echo returns—with the presence of specific fish and zooplankton species or taxa.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the first stage of the project, we are focusing on developing
&lt;a href="https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202405-asa-ottawa-hake/">an echogram segmentation model to identify Pacific hake&lt;/a>, a keystone species and the largest fishery stock on the west coast of the US. Identifying hake on echograms is more challenging compared to many other fish species, due to their polymorphic appearance and diffused school boundaries. We found that neural networks' large learning capacity are well-suited to address these complexities. However, as in many other domains, organizing echosounder data with survey metadata and sorting expert annotations remains a significant bottleneck in fully leveraging these technologies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Moving forward, we aim to expand the model to include other ecologically and commercially important fish species in the California Current ecosystem, and incorporate other analytical methods, such as Bayesian inversion techniques, to improve acoustic data interpretation and biomass estimation accuracy.&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- To take full advantage of these large and complex new datasets, in this project we aim to combine the development of machine learning methodology with a cloud-based workflow to accelerate the extraction of biological information from fisheries acoustic data. Our group has developed and used [Echopype](https://echopype.readthedocs.io/en/stable/), a Raw Sonar Backscatter data parsing Python package, and [Echoregions](https://echoregions.readthedocs.io/en/latest/), an Echoview annotation data parsing Python package. Transferring data from Echoview and proprietary echosounder formats to Python data products enables seamless integration with a rich ecosystem of scientific computing tools developed by a vast community of open-source contributors, thus allowing us to use our data to train deep learning models to predict regions of interest in echograms.
&lt;img src="featured.png" alt="Fisheries Acoustics"> -->
&lt;p align="center">
&lt;img src="featured.png" alt="" style="width:1000px"/>
&lt;b>Echogram examples showing the deep learning model predicts regions similar to human expert annotations.&lt;/b>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This project is in close collaboration with the
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/west-coast/sustainable-fisheries/fisheries-engineering-and-acoustic-technologies-team" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fisheries Engineering and Acoustics Technology (FEAT) team&lt;/a> at the NOAA Fisheries
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/about/northwest-fisheries-science-center" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Northwest Fisheries science center (NWFSC)&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding agency&lt;/strong>: NOAA Fisheries&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Scalable, cloud-native processing of water column sonar data</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project_others/2021-cloud-workflows/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 16:56:36 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project_others/2021-cloud-workflows/</guid><description>&lt;p>Scientists commonly use active sonar systems to collect data about mid-trophic level animals like zooplankton and small fish, which play an important role in the marine ecosystems. Echosounders, or fish-finders, are high-frequency sonar systems that emit pulses of sound and record the reflections from animals, the seabed, and other objects. These instruments have been proven to be more efficient and effective for collecting data over a large survey area or a long time period than many other sampling methods, such as underwater imaging and net trawls. This technology has been widely adopted by the ocean science and commercial fishing communities and more recently has been integrated with autonomous vehicles, resulting in a massive amount of data. However, these datasets can be difficult to analyze and are often underutilized. We will address this issue by adopting and advancing data standards, developing a streamlined data processing workflow, and integrating open-source software tools that capitalize on recent advancements in cloud computing technologies to efficiently transform large quantities of ocean sonar data into information that is useful for exploring, monitoring, and managing living marine resources.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding agency&lt;/strong>: NOAA Office of Ocean Exploration and Research
&lt;a href="https://oceanexplorer.noaa.gov/news/oer-updates/2021/fy21-ffo-schedule.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FY2021 grants&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The open-source "Echostack" for flexible and scalable echosounder data processing</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/echostack/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/echostack/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://storymaps.arcgis.com/stories/e245977def474bdba60952f30576908f" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Water column sonar data collected by echosounders&lt;/a> are essential for fisheries and marine ecosystem research, enabling the detection, classification, and quantification of fish and zooplankton from many different ocean observing platforms. However, the broad usage of these data has been hindered by the lack of modular software tools that allow flexible composition of data processing workflows that incorporate powerful analytical tools in the scientific Python ecosystem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We address this gap by developing &lt;strong>Echostack&lt;/strong>, a suite of open-source Python software packages that leverage existing distributed computing and cloud-interfacing libraries to support intuitive and scalable data access, processing, and interpretation. These tools can be used individually or orchestrated together, which we demonstrate in example use cases for a fisheries acoustic-trawl survey.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Below is a summary of the Echostack packages:&lt;/p>
&lt;p align="center">
&lt;img src="echostack_summary.png" alt="Echostack summary" style="width:1000px"/>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For more information, check out the code repositories below:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echopype" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echopype&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Check out the our
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/icesjms/fsae133" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echopype paper&lt;/a> in the ICES Journal of Marine Science&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echopop" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echopop&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Learn more on the
&lt;a href="../../project_others/echopop/">Echopop project page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echoshader" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echoshader&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echoregions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echoregions&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echodataflow" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echodataflow&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>These packages are accompanied by a set of
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echolevels" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echolevels&lt;/a> that categorize data products at different workflow stages to enhance data understanding and provenance tracking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out Wu-Jung&amp;rsquo;s talk at SciPy 2024 and the associated
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.25080/WXRH8633" target="_blank" rel="noopener">paper&lt;/a> in the proceedings!
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YRFxMGisGww" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>NOAA Fisheries&lt;/li>
&lt;li>NOAA Office of Ocean Exploration and Research
&lt;a href="https://oceanexplorer.noaa.gov/news/oer-updates/2021/fy21-ffo-schedule.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FY2021 grants&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Echopop: biomass estimation for Pacific Hake</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project_others/echopop/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 17:02:36 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project_others/echopop/</guid><description>&lt;p>Echopop is a software used for processing backscatter measurements and biological data collected from acoustic-trawl surveys to estimate population estimates and other metrics. The development of this software has been primarily focused on surveys targeting Pacific hake (&lt;strong>see below information for more details&lt;/strong>), but the goal is to generalize the software in the future for broader fisheries community use.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/west-coast/sustainable-fisheries/fisheries-engineering-and-acoustic-technologies-team" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fisheries Engineering and Acoustics Technology (FEAT) team&lt;/a> at the NOAA Fisheries
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/about/northwest-fisheries-science-center" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Northwest Fisheries Science Center (NWFSC)&lt;/a> collaborates with
&lt;a href="https://www.dfo-mpo.gc.ca/index-eng.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fisheries and Oceans Canada (DFO) - Pacific Region&lt;/a> to estimate total biomass of
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/species/pacific-whiting" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pacific hake (&lt;i>Merluccius productus&lt;/i>)&lt;/a> by incorporating acoustic and biological trawl data from the
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/west-coast/science-data/joint-us-canada-integrated-ecosystem-and-pacific-hake-acoustic-trawl-survey" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Joint U.S.-Canada Integrated Ecosystem and Pacific Hake Acoustic-Trawl Survey&lt;/a> (aka the &amp;ldquo;Hake survey&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These biomass estimates are the inputs for the stock assessment of hake and need to be completed in an efficient and timely manner after the survey. The biomass estimates are currently produced by a suite of Matlab scripts operated by a single user, and the analysis procedures are not easily adaptable by other FEAT/DFO team members. The central objective of this project is to provide a well-documented open-source
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echopop" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Python software package&lt;/a> (&lt;code>echopop&lt;/code>) that contains the core computational functionality of the current Matlab EchoPro program and provides basic visualization of the analysis results.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The new software package (currently
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echopop/releases/latest" target="_blank" rel="noopener">version 0.4.0&lt;/a> and available on
&lt;a href="https://pypi.org/project/echopop/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PyPi&lt;/a>) contains an expanded
&lt;a href="https://echopop.readthedocs.io/en/latest/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">documentation&lt;/a> that details the underlying theory and algorithmic implementation that help facilitate reproducibility. Other features include an
&lt;a href="https://echopop.readthedocs.io/en/latest/api.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Application Programming Interface (API)&lt;/a> that can be invoked in a reproducible manner, a flexible analysis configuration that allows for both machine and human-readable parameterizations, and interactive Jupyter notebooks that exemplify various workflows
&lt;a href="https://echopop.readthedocs.io/en/latest/example_notebooks/example_echopop_workflow.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ranging from initial data processing to kriging&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding agency&lt;/strong>: NOAA Fisheries, NOAA NWFSC&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Echopype</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project_others/echopype/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 14:50:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project_others/echopype/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;code>Echopype&lt;/code>&lt;/strong> is an open-source Python package aimed at
&lt;a href="https://echopype.readthedocs.io/en/latest/why.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">enhancing the interoperability and scalability&lt;/a>
in processing ocean sonar data for biological information.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I started building this package in early 2018 when I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find an affordable tool that
allow easy access and manipulation of echosounder data collected by
different sonar models.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For the latest updates, check out our repo at: &lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echopype">https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echopype&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out my talk at SciPy 2019 that discussed the goals and philosophy of echopype:
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qboH7MyHrpU" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Pattern discovery from long-term echosounder time series</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/2019-ooi-mtx-decomp/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 14:50:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/2019-ooi-mtx-decomp/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding agency&lt;/strong>: National Science Foundation
&lt;a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1849930&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Award #1849930&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Interoperable and scalable echosounder data processing with Echopype</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/publication/2024-lee-etal-echopype/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/publication/2024-lee-etal-echopype/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Echostack: An open-source Python software toolbox that democratizes water column sonar dataand processing</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202407-scipy-echostack/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 14:20:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202407-scipy-echostack/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Variability and influence of fisheries acoustic echogram annotations on machine learning applications</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202405-asa-ottawa-hake/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202405-asa-ottawa-hake/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Two Pieces of the Same Puzzle: Active and Passive Acoustics for Cross-Trophic Marine Ecosystem Monitoring Part II</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202405-asa-ottawa-school/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202405-asa-ottawa-school/</guid><description/></item><item><title>A ship-to-cloud machine learning pipeline built on the open-source Python Echostack software tools</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202404-wgfast-ship2cloud/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202404-wgfast-ship2cloud/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Scalable and configurable echosounder data workflows</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202404-wgfast-echodataflow/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202404-wgfast-echodataflow/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Understanding echoes</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202205-asa-denver-keynote/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 16:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202205-asa-denver-keynote/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Updates from Echopype developers: changes and roadmap</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202204-wgfast-echopype/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 18:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202204-wgfast-echopype/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Summarizing low-dimensional patterns in long-term echosounder time series from the U.S. Ocean Observatories Initiative network</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202204-wgfast-ooi-nmf/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 18:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202204-wgfast-ooi-nmf/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Scalable, interoperable processing of water column sonar data for biological applications using the echopype Python package</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202110-ioos-dmac/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 15:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202110-ioos-dmac/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Building a toolbox for studying marine ecology using large ocean sonar datasets</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202110-uw-data-sci/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 16:30:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202110-uw-data-sci/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>