<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Our values | Echospace @ UW</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/values/</link><atom:link href="https://uw-echospace.github.io/values/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Our values</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://uw-echospace.github.io/images/icon_hu9a3e81eca2a83564e549c2cdc32b0637_27049_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>Our values</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/values/</link></image><item><title>Code of Conduct &amp; What we value</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/values/2023-10-coc-values/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/values/2023-10-coc-values/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="why">Why&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We respect and want to take advantage of the diversity of background and expertise in the group.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We also want to create an optimal learning and research environment for everyone.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="code-of-conduct">Code of Conduct&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Echospace is dedicated to providing a harassment-free experience for everyone, regardless of gender, gender identity and expression, age, sexual orientation, disability, physical appearance, body size, race, or religion (or lack thereof). We do not tolerate harassment of group members in any form. Sexual language and imagery is not appropriate for any group venue, including meetings, presentations, or discussions, and in both physical and online spaces.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-we-value">What we value&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Be proactive
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Say hello to people you meet at work (in the morning when you come to work, etc)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Be on time and respect other’s time, communicate if you don’t have time&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Don’t be afraid of being wrong and ask, and answer to questions from others kindly&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Be open to change&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Communication
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Respect other person’s background may be different from yours&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Be welcoming to others’ perspectives and what makes them tick, what excites them&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Don’t assume people know or don’t know what you’re talking about, it is ok and often better to just ask&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When there are different opinions, try to convince others by reasoning, and avoid being dismissive because of others’ career stages or rank&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Strive to communicate, both when we don’t think we understand what the other person is saying and when we think we are not being understood (misunderstandings)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Acknowledge contributions from others&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ask questions and provide feedback kindly
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Use “we” instead of “you”&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Use sandwich method: start with positive statement, follow with the comment “have you consider XYZ”, and end with positive affirmation/offer support&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Provide constructive feedback, elaborate on your comments, and be willing to explain more&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Value listening to others, and asking respectful questions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Provide positive feedback too!&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Group interaction and collaboration
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Have clear expectations and communicate openly, to avoid last minute surprises&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ensure everyone has the opportunity to participate both online and in person&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Give opportunities to others to speak first&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Make accommodations for personal emergencies&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Help each other grow
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Provide opportunities for peer mentoring&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sharing opportunities in the group that others might be interested in (or would want to be involved in)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Enable and encourage growth by everyone in the group, in directions that align with what they’re interested in&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Be comfortable bringing up issues or obstacles that hold you back from getting work done&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>