<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>cloud computing | Echospace @ UW</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/tag/cloud-computing/</link><atom:link href="https://uw-echospace.github.io/tag/cloud-computing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>cloud computing</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 14:50:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://uw-echospace.github.io/images/icon_hu9a3e81eca2a83564e549c2cdc32b0637_27049_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>cloud computing</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/tag/cloud-computing/</link></image><item><title>Machine learning in fisheries acoustics</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/2021-hake-workflow/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 17:02:36 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/2021-hake-workflow/</guid><description>&lt;p>Active acoustic data collected with scientific echosounders from acoustic surveys have become essential for stock assessment in fisheries resources management. Over the past three decades, a wide suite of physics-based acoustic scattering models were developed to allow translating acoustic observations to biological quantities, such as biomass and abundance, for different marine organisms. In parallel, quantitative scientific echosounders have progressed from specialized equipment to one of the standard instruments on fisheries survey vessels.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To take full advantage of these large and complex new datasets, in this project we aim to combine the development of machine learning methodology with a cloud-based workflow to accelerate the extraction of biological information from fisheries acoustic data. This project is in close collaboration with the
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/west-coast/sustainable-fisheries/fisheries-engineering-and-acoustic-technologies-team" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fisheries Engineering and Acoustics Technology (FEAT) team&lt;/a> at the NOAA Fisheries
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/about/northwest-fisheries-science-center" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Northwest Fisheries science center (NWFSC)&lt;/a> and uses data collected in the past 20 years off the west coast of the U.S. from the
&lt;a href="https://www.fisheries.noaa.gov/west-coast/science-data/joint-us-canada-integrated-ecosystem-and-pacific-hake-acoustic-trawl-survey" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Joint U.S.-Canada Integrated Ecosystem and Pacific Hake Acoustic-Trawl Survey&lt;/a> (aka the &amp;ldquo;Hake survey&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding agency&lt;/strong>: NOAA Fisheries&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Postdoc position for machine learning in fisheries/ocean acoustics</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/position/2021-06-30-postdoc-hake-ml/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 14:50:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/position/2021-06-30-postdoc-hake-ml/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="location">Location&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Seattle, WA, USA&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="open-date">Open Date&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>June 30, 2021&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="deadline">Deadline&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Open until filled. Review of materials will start immediately.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="description">Description&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We are looking for a highly motivated and independent individual to join the
&lt;a href="https://uw-echospace.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echospace&lt;/a> group at the University of Washington to conduct research at the intersection of fisheries/ocean acoustics and machine learning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The postdoc will develop and apply machine learning methodologies to extract identification and distribution information of fish and zooplankton from large volumes of water column sonar data collected over the past 20 years off the west coast of the U.S. The project is in close collaboration with the NOAA Fisheries Northwest Fisheries Science Center (NWFSC) with a primary goal of developing a high-throughput echosounder data analysis pipeline to contribute to fishery stock assessment and ecosystem-based management. In addition, the postdoc will have opportunities to develop skills including cloud computing and software engineering as integrated components of their work within Echospace and interact with the vibrant ocean sciences and data science communities at UW and in Seattle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The UW Echospace group, based jointly at the
&lt;a href="https://www.apl.washington.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Applied Physics Laboratory&lt;/a> (APL) and
&lt;a href="https://escience.washington.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">eScience Institute&lt;/a>, is a highly collaborative research group with members with diverse backgrounds and experiences. Our research centers around acoustic ocean sensing and data science, and spans a broad spectrum from development of computational methods, open source software, cloud applications, to joint analysis of acoustic observations and ocean environmental variables. We are committed to provide a supportive environment for group members to grow and contribute to the acoustics, oceanography, and data science communities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The anticipated start date of this position is in the Fall of 2021. The initial appointment period is 18 months, with renewal contingent on satisfactory performance and funding availability (also see Limitations on Appointment below). Promotional opportunities following the completion of the postdoc appointment are possible subject to availability of funds and demonstration of an interest in developing independent research initiatives during the appointment. The candidate is encouraged to apply for the
&lt;a href="https://escience.washington.edu/uw-data-science-postdoctoral-fellow/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UW Data Science Postdoctoral Fellowship&lt;/a> and the
&lt;a href="https://apply.interfolio.com/86009" target="_blank" rel="noopener">APL Science and Engineering Enrichment and Development (SEED) Postdoctoral Scholar Program&lt;/a> in parallel with this position.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="qualifications">Qualifications&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The candidate will hold a PhD degree (earned or nearing completion of) in acoustics, oceanography, computational sciences, or a related field, and have a track record of first-author, peer-reviewed publications, programming experience (Python, R, Matlab, or similar), and prior research experience in relevant research domains, such as ocean acoustics, fisheries acoustics, machine learning, statistics, data visualization, and physical or biological oceanography. Familiarity with echosounder data and analysis techniques, and experience applying machine learning methods to scientific problems are preferred. They are expected to have excellent communication skills, the experience and/or ability to work in a team environment, and a strong interest in interdisciplinary research approaches.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="application-instructions">Application Instructions&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Please upload your application materials via Interfolio at &lt;a href="https://apply.interfolio.com/89869">https://apply.interfolio.com/89869&lt;/a>. Include the following materials:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>CV including a list of publications (include GitHub handle if available)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cover letter with a brief description of present and future research interests&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A list of three references and their contact information&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>For questions about the position, please reach out to Dr. Wu-Jung Lee (&lt;a href="mailto:leewj@uw.edu">leewj@uw.edu&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To request disability accommodation in the application process, please contact the UW&amp;rsquo;s Disability Services Office at 206-543-6450, or 206-543-6452 (TTY), or &lt;a href="mailto:dso@uw.edu">dso@uw.edu&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="_limitations-on-appointment_">&lt;em>Limitations on Appointment&lt;/em>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;em>In compliance with regulations at University of Washington, cumulative length of postdoctoral appointment may not exceed 5 years, including postdoctoral experience(s) at other institutions. Postdoctoral Scholars are engaged in full-time mentored advanced training to enhance professional skills and research independence, and perform primarily research and scholarship under the direction and supervision of University faculty mentors.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Postdoctoral scholars are represented by UAW 4121 and are subject to the collective bargaining agreement, unless agreed exclusion criteria apply. For more information, please visit the University of Washington Labor Relations website (UAW Contract).&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="_equal-employment-opportunity-statement_">&lt;em>Equal Employment Opportunity Statement&lt;/em>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;em>University of Washington is an affirmative action and equal opportunity employer. All qualified applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, color, creed, religion, national origin, sex, sexual orientation, marital status, pregnancy, genetic information, gender identity or expression, age, disability, or protected veteran status.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="_commitment-to-diversity_">&lt;em>Commitment to Diversity&lt;/em>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;em>The University of Washington is committed to building diversity among its faculty, librarian, staff, and student communities, and articulates that commitment in the
&lt;a href="http://www.washington.edu/diversity/diversity-blueprint/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UW Diversity Blueprint&lt;/a>. Additionally, the University’s Faculty Code recognizes faculty efforts in research, teaching and/or service that address diversity and equal opportunity as important contributions to
&lt;a href="https://www.washington.edu/admin/rules/policies/FCG/FCCH24.html#2432" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a faculty member’s academic profile and responsibilities&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>