<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>community engagement | Echospace @ UW</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/tag/community-engagement/</link><atom:link href="https://uw-echospace.github.io/tag/community-engagement/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>community engagement</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://uw-echospace.github.io/images/icon_hu9a3e81eca2a83564e549c2cdc32b0637_27049_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>community engagement</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/tag/community-engagement/</link></image><item><title>BOAT: Bridge to Ocean Acoustics and Technology</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/boat/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 17:02:36 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/boat/</guid><description>&lt;p>Ocean acoustics is an interdisciplinary field in which researchers focus on measuring, modeling, and understanding acoustic phenomena of oceanographical, geological, biological, and anthropogenic sources. However, despite its inherent interdisciplinary nature, Ocean acoustics research currently has limited presence in most US institutions and is typically viewed as a highly niched field.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The
&lt;a href="https://boat-ocean-acoustics.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bridge to Ocean Acoustics and Technology (BOAT)&lt;/a> program aims to broaden access to ocean acoustics by empowering learners to explore and advance the field through collaboration and shared knowledge, focusing on:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Developing open, executable, and web-hosted tutorials that encapsulate fundamental ocean acoustics knowledge and techniques as living documents.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Growing the ocean acoustics education and research community through interactive and collaborative workshops.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In the current pilot phase, we will host two education workshops to provide a hands-on introduction to ocean acoustics—from fundamental concepts to real-world applications—using interactive
&lt;a href="https://jupyter.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jupyter notebooks&lt;/a>. We will cover topics broadly applicable to both active and passive acoustics, with hands-on experience using echosounder and hydrophone datasets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our goal is to create open tutorials that can 1) be adapted to various educational settings, including regular university courses or summer workshops, and 2) serve as blueprints for further developing in-depth resources on specific ocean acoustics topics.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>See the
&lt;a href="https://boat-ocean-acoustics.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">BOAT website&lt;/a> for information for the two upcoming workshops in
&lt;a href="https://boat-ocean-acoustics.github.io/workshop_seattle.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Seattle&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://boat-ocean-acoustics.github.io/workshop_new_orleans.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New Orleans&lt;/a>!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding Agency:&lt;/strong> Office of Naval Research, Ocean Acoustics Program&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>UBNA passive acoustic monitoring project</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project_others/2022-ubna-pam/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 17:02:36 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project_others/2022-ubna-pam/</guid><description>&lt;p>Understanding how echolocators make use of sound to navigate their surroundings has great potential for informing the design of advanced acoustic sensing technologies. Although much has already been studied in laboratory experiments, technology has just started catching up to allow researchers to study echolocation-related processes in the wild. Advancements in passive acoustic monitoring tools have made it affordable to conduct long-term acoustic surveys on animals in the wild. Echolocators, like bats, are well-suited for monitoring using simple passive acoustic techniques because of their use of acoustics and navgitaion in air.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this project, we sought to collect long-term acoustic data using Audiomoths from an urban natural area called the Union Bay Natural Area at the University of Washington. With this data, we hope to uncover questions on how environmental conditions influence how bats choose to forage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding agency&lt;/strong>:
&lt;a href="https://www.washington.edu/research/or/royalty-research-fund-rrf/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Washington Royalty Research Fund&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Passive acoustic monitoring in the Union Bay Natural Area</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/ubna-pam/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/ubna-pam/</guid><description>&lt;p>Passive acoustic monitoring (PAM) has become a useful technique for monitoring soniferous animals in both terrestrial and marine habitats, and has in recent years been particularly bolstered by the broader availability and accessibility of low-cost recording devices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this project, we deploy low-cost
&lt;a href="https://www.openacousticdevices.info/audiomoth" target="_blank" rel="noopener">AudioMoth&lt;/a> recorders at multiple sites in the
&lt;a href="https://botanicgardens.uw.edu/center-for-urban-horticulture/visit/union-bay-natural-area/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Union Bay Natural Area&lt;/a>, right on the eastern edge of the University of Washington, Seattle campus. Since the project began in fall 2021, we have collected over 30 TB of recordings that are embedded with sounds from a wide variety of animals (e.g., birds, bats, frogs) and anthopogenic sources (e.g., airplanes, football stadium roars).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Beyond generating a rich dataset, the project fieldwork and data analysis provides an accesible entry point for students to engage in real-world bioacoustics research, with hands-on data science and instrumentation opportunities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We have leveraged this dataset to investigate the
&lt;a href="https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202405-aditya-duty-cycle/">impact of duty cycle recording on bat monitoring&lt;/a> and support multiple capstone projects in the
&lt;a href="https://www.washington.edu/datasciencemasters/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UW Data Sciene Master&amp;rsquo;s Program&lt;/a>, focused on developing open-source, cloud-hosted workflows for analyzing large PAM datasets. With these tools in place, going forward we plan to characterize the seasonal soundscape fluctuations in UBNA with respect to weather/climate events, and find opportunities to expand this effort to a community monitoring program in the Greater Seattle area.&lt;/p>
&lt;p align="center">
&lt;img src="featured.png" alt="UBNA bat activity grid" style="width:600px"/>
&lt;b>Bat call activity detected in two UBNA sites in 2022.&lt;/b>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding&lt;/strong>:
&lt;a href="https://www.washington.edu/research/or/royalty-research-fund-rrf/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UW Royalty Research Fund&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Scalable, cloud-native processing of water column sonar data</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project_others/2021-cloud-workflows/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 16:56:36 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project_others/2021-cloud-workflows/</guid><description>&lt;p>Scientists commonly use active sonar systems to collect data about mid-trophic level animals like zooplankton and small fish, which play an important role in the marine ecosystems. Echosounders, or fish-finders, are high-frequency sonar systems that emit pulses of sound and record the reflections from animals, the seabed, and other objects. These instruments have been proven to be more efficient and effective for collecting data over a large survey area or a long time period than many other sampling methods, such as underwater imaging and net trawls. This technology has been widely adopted by the ocean science and commercial fishing communities and more recently has been integrated with autonomous vehicles, resulting in a massive amount of data. However, these datasets can be difficult to analyze and are often underutilized. We will address this issue by adopting and advancing data standards, developing a streamlined data processing workflow, and integrating open-source software tools that capitalize on recent advancements in cloud computing technologies to efficiently transform large quantities of ocean sonar data into information that is useful for exploring, monitoring, and managing living marine resources.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding agency&lt;/strong>: NOAA Office of Ocean Exploration and Research
&lt;a href="https://oceanexplorer.noaa.gov/news/oer-updates/2021/fy21-ffo-schedule.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FY2021 grants&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The open-source "Echostack" for flexible and scalable echosounder data processing</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/echostack/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/project/echostack/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://storymaps.arcgis.com/stories/e245977def474bdba60952f30576908f" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Water column sonar data collected by echosounders&lt;/a> are essential for fisheries and marine ecosystem research, enabling the detection, classification, and quantification of fish and zooplankton from many different ocean observing platforms. However, the broad usage of these data has been hindered by the lack of modular software tools that allow flexible composition of data processing workflows that incorporate powerful analytical tools in the scientific Python ecosystem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We address this gap by developing &lt;strong>Echostack&lt;/strong>, a suite of open-source Python software packages that leverage existing distributed computing and cloud-interfacing libraries to support intuitive and scalable data access, processing, and interpretation. These tools can be used individually or orchestrated together, which we demonstrate in example use cases for a fisheries acoustic-trawl survey.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Below is a summary of the Echostack packages:&lt;/p>
&lt;p align="center">
&lt;img src="echostack_summary.png" alt="Echostack summary" style="width:1000px"/>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For more information, check out the code repositories below:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echopype" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echopype&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Check out the our
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/icesjms/fsae133" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echopype paper&lt;/a> in the ICES Journal of Marine Science&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echopop" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echopop&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Learn more on the
&lt;a href="../../project_others/echopop/">Echopop project page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echoshader" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echoshader&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echoregions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echoregions&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echodataflow" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echodataflow&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>These packages are accompanied by a set of
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OSOceanAcoustics/echolevels" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echolevels&lt;/a> that categorize data products at different workflow stages to enhance data understanding and provenance tracking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out Wu-Jung&amp;rsquo;s talk at SciPy 2024 and the associated
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.25080/WXRH8633" target="_blank" rel="noopener">paper&lt;/a> in the proceedings!
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YRFxMGisGww" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Funding&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>NOAA Fisheries&lt;/li>
&lt;li>NOAA Office of Ocean Exploration and Research
&lt;a href="https://oceanexplorer.noaa.gov/news/oer-updates/2021/fy21-ffo-schedule.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FY2021 grants&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Interoperable and scalable echosounder data processing with Echopype</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/publication/2024-lee-etal-echopype/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/publication/2024-lee-etal-echopype/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Echostack: An open-source Python software toolbox that democratizes water column sonar dataand processing</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202407-scipy-echostack/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 14:20:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202407-scipy-echostack/</guid><description/></item><item><title>A ship-to-cloud machine learning pipeline built on the open-source Python Echostack software tools</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202404-wgfast-ship2cloud/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202404-wgfast-ship2cloud/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Scalable and configurable echosounder data workflows</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202404-wgfast-echodataflow/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202404-wgfast-echodataflow/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Understanding echoes</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202205-asa-denver-keynote/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 16:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202205-asa-denver-keynote/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Updates from Echopype developers: changes and roadmap</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202204-wgfast-echopype/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 18:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202204-wgfast-echopype/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Scalable, interoperable processing of water column sonar data for biological applications using the echopype Python package</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202110-ioos-dmac/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 15:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202110-ioos-dmac/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Building a toolbox for studying marine ecology using large ocean sonar datasets</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202110-uw-data-sci/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 16:30:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202110-uw-data-sci/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>