<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Valentina Staneva | Echospace @ UW</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/author/valentina-staneva/</link><atom:link href="https://uw-echospace.github.io/author/valentina-staneva/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Valentina Staneva</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 00:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://uw-echospace.github.io/images/icon_hu9a3e81eca2a83564e549c2cdc32b0637_27049_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>Valentina Staneva</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/author/valentina-staneva/</link></image><item><title>Postdoc position for machine learning in fisheries/ocean acoustics for ecological applications</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/position/2022-08-22-postdoc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/position/2022-08-22-postdoc/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="location">Location&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Seattle, WA, USA&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="deadline">Deadline&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Open until filled. Review of materials will start immediately.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="description">Description&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We are looking for a highly motivated early-career scientist to join the
&lt;a href="https://uw-echospace.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Echospace&lt;/a> group at the University of Washington to conduct research at the intersection of fisheries/ocean acoustics and machine learning. The postdoc will develop computational methods to extract information from large volumes of ocean acoustic data. The initial project will focus on automatic identification of fish and zooplankton in echosounder data collected by ships, with expansions to integrate additional active/passive acoustic and environmental data streams from collocated moorings in the highly productive
&lt;a href="https://tos.org/oceanography/article/why-is-the-northern-end-of-the-california-current-system-so-productive" target="_blank" rel="noopener">northern California Current System&lt;/a>. The project is in close collaboration with the NOAA Northwest Fisheries Science Center. The successful candidate will have a wide range of opportunities to develop new projects, build integrated skills across physics-based models, data-driven methods, and cloud computing, and interact with the vibrant ocean sciences and data science communities at UW and in Seattle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The expected start date of this position is in the fall/winter of 2022. The initial appointment period is one year, with extension contingent on satisfactory performance and funding availability (also see Limitations on Appointment below). Promotion following the completion of the appointment is possible subject to demonstration of an interest and the ability to develop independent research initiatives during the appointment. The candidate is encouraged to apply for the
&lt;a href="https://escience.washington.edu/uw-data-science-postdoctoral-fellow/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UW Data Science Postdoctoral Fellowship&lt;/a> in parallel with this position.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The
&lt;a href="https://uw-echospace.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UW Echospace&lt;/a> group is a highly collaborative research group based jointly at the
&lt;a href="https://www.apl.washington.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Applied Physics Laboratory (APL)&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://escience.washington.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">eScience Institute&lt;/a>. Our research centers around acoustic ocean sensing and data science, and spans a broad spectrum from development of computational methods and open-source software to joint analysis of acoustic observations and ocean environmental variables. We are committed to provide a supportive environment for group members to grow and contribute to the acoustics, oceanography, and data science communities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For other opportunities to work with us, see
&lt;a href="https://uw-echospace.github.io/position/fellowships/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this page&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="qualifications">Qualifications&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The candidate will hold a PhD degree (earned or nearing completion of) in one of the following fields: acoustics, oceanography, fisheries, statistics, or a related field in computational sciences. They will have a track record of first-author, peer-reviewed publication(s) in related domains and experience programming in Python, R, Matlab, or similar. Familiarity with ocean/fisheries acoustics or experience applying machine learning methods to scientific problems are preferred. They are expected to have excellent communication skills, the ability and desire to work in a team environment, and a strong interest in interdisciplinary research approaches.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="application-instructions">Application Instructions&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Please submit your application to Drs. Wu-Jung Lee (&lt;a href="mailto:leewj@uw.edu">leewj@uw.edu&lt;/a>) and Valentina Staneva (&lt;a href="mailto:vms16@uw.edu">vms16@uw.edu&lt;/a>) with the following materials: 1) CV including a list of publication(s); 2) cover letter with brief description of present and future research interests; 3) a list of three references and their contact information. Informal inquiries are welcome.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="_limitations-on-appointment_">&lt;em>Limitations on Appointment&lt;/em>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;em>In compliance with regulations at University of Washington, cumulative length of postdoctoral appointment may not exceed 5 years, including postdoctoral experience(s) at other institutions. Postdoctoral Scholars are engaged in full-time mentored advanced training to enhance professional skills and research independence, and perform primarily research and scholarship under the direction and supervision of University faculty mentors.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Postdoctoral scholars are represented by UAW 4121 and are subject to the collective bargaining agreement, unless agreed exclusion criteria apply. For more information, please visit the University of Washington Labor Relations website (UAW Contract).&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="_equal-employment-opportunity-statement_">&lt;em>Equal Employment Opportunity Statement&lt;/em>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;em>University of Washington is an affirmative action and equal opportunity employer. All qualified applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, color, creed, religion, national origin, sex, sexual orientation, marital status, pregnancy, genetic information, gender identity or expression, age, disability, or protected veteran status.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="_commitment-to-diversity_">&lt;em>Commitment to Diversity&lt;/em>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>_The University of Washington is committed to building diversity among its faculty, librarian, staff, and student communities, and articulates that commitment in the UW Diversity Blueprint (&lt;a href="http://www.washington.edu/diversity/diversity-blueprint/)">http://www.washington.edu/diversity/diversity-blueprint/)&lt;/a>. Additionally, the University&amp;rsquo;s Faculty Code recognizes faculty efforts in research, teaching and/or service that address diversity and equal opportunity as important contributions to a faculty member&amp;rsquo;s academic profile and responsibilities (&lt;a href="https://www.washington.edu/admin/rules/policies/FCG/FCCH24.html#2432)._">https://www.washington.edu/admin/rules/policies/FCG/FCCH24.html#2432)._&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Opportunities at Echospace</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/position/fellowships/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/position/fellowships/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="general-information">General information&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We welcome researchers and students with diverse backgrounds to come work with us in Echospace! If you are interested but do not find a specific position posted, feel free to reach out to us directly. Please include a cover letter and a CV/resume when initiating the contact, so that we have a better idea what you are looking for.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="fellowship-opportunities">Fellowship opportunities&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Below is a list of fellowship opportunities within and outside of UW. Relevant areas include but are not limited to fisheries and ocean acoustics, animal echolocation (bats and dolphins), marine ecology, and environmental data science. Feel free to reach out to us for questions and discussion.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="postdoc-fellowships">Postdoc fellowships&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="university-of-washington">University of Washington&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://ap.washington.edu/ahr/position-details/?job_id=99111" target="_blank" rel="noopener">APL SEED Postdoctoral Scholar Program&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://cicoes.uw.edu/education/postdoc-program/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cooperative Institute for Climate, Ocean, and Ecosystem Studies (CICOES) postdoctoral fellowship&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.wrfseattle.org/grants/wrf-postdoctoral-fellowships/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Washington Research Foundation (WRF) Postdoctoral Fellowship&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="external">External&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://beta.nsf.gov/funding/opportunities/ocean-sciences-postdoctoral-research-fellowships-oce-prf-0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NSF Ocean Sciences (OCE) Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (OCE-PRF)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://beta.nsf.gov/funding/opportunities/ear-postdoctoral-fellowships-ear-pf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NSF Division of Earth Sciences (EAR) Postdoctoral Fellowships (EAR-PF)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://acousticalsociety.org/fellowships-and-scholarships/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Acoustical Society of America (ASA) Hunt Postdoctoral Research fellowship&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="graduate-fellowships">Graduate fellowships&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.nsfgrfp.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NSF Graduate Research Fellowships Program (GRFP)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="undergraduate-fellowships">Undergraduate fellowships&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://expd.uw.edu/mge/apply/research/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mary Gates Research Scholarship&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Updates from Echopype developers: changes and roadmap</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202204-wgfast-echopype/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 18:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202204-wgfast-echopype/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Summarizing low-dimensional patterns in long-term echosounder time series from the U.S. Ocean Observatories Initiative network</title><link>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202204-wgfast-ooi-nmf/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 18:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://uw-echospace.github.io/talk/202204-wgfast-ooi-nmf/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>